{
  "reference_number": "32",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Carbon sequestration in the soil needs to be recognised by the ETS if farming is to be included. This can be achieved by measuring\n the organic matter in a soil annually. Moreover legislation needs to be included which requires any nitrate application to soil being\n\n required to include a carbon source with it such as humates, humic acid, fulvic acid or biomass. The added carbon will have the\n increased benefit of increasing the cation exchange capacity of the soil increasing the soils organic matter and its ability to reduce\n\n nitrate leachate into our water ways. Both of these items will incentivise farmers to change their practice, impact significantly the\n proposed carbon budgeting, improve environmental health and other flow on benefits pertaining to animal and human health."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "If international carbon units are to be used there should be a phase out plan for these unless there are extenuating circumstances"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Time is running out we need to be resolute."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Resolute is an ideal for the long term whereas flexibility in the short term is required"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The exceptional circumstances need to be specified and if this option is exercised a plan needs to be provided that brings us back\n\non track before the relief action is taken."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "All carbon sequestration needs to be recognised this includes what occurs in the soil."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "it is important that there is some accountability from the government in regard to recognising the recommendations of the\ncommission as the setting of the carbon price has a big impact upon the goals being set in the the Zero Carbon Bill."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "All the areas proposed are relevant but we need to have a full input from the agricultural/horticultural sector as methane from\n\nagriculture is a major source of Carbon in our Economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Getting to zero carbon is important but we need to manage the process and climate change is a result of not-zero carbon - they are\ninterlinked and need to be considered in unison."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Care needs to be taken not to make this bill too cumbersome thereby increasing the time to implementation."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Provision could be made for this entity to be set up in the bill but perhaps its brief could form part of the commissions role."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is of paramount importance that the soils role be recognised in this issue in order to encourage farming practice to increase the\nsoils organic matter. \"A great deal of the carbon once stored in the soil is now stored in the atmosphere - 30% of CO2 can be\n\ncountered by humus-building (based upon just the top 15cm)\" Graeme Saite . Humus Saves the World, Ted Talk. Moreover it has\nbeen estimated that a 1% increase in US crop lands alone would take take 4.5 billion tonnes of CO2 from the atmosphere and return\n\nit to the soil. Recognition of this principle and applied to NZ will have huge benefit to the proposed Carbon budgets."
    }
  ]
}
